Finding Aid for the Henry Lee Swint Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Henry Lee Swint Papers
1933-1978
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0429
33.36 linear_feet
The Henry Lee Swint Papers date from 1933 to 1978 and are comprised primarily of correspondence, writings, and research notes. Swint carried on an extensive correspondence with students, former students, and colleagues at other institutions, mainly discussing research interests and personal concerns. A more limited correspondence with faculty and other colleagues at Vanderbilt contains information regarding administrative matters, including controversial subjects such as the 1960 dismissal of Divinity School student James Lawson for participating in civil rights demonstrations in Nashville. The collection also includes a fairly extensive file of speeches and lecture notes, book reviews, article manuscripts and offprints, correspondence regarding Swint’s two books, and research notes on Vanderbilt’s history.
Biographical Sketch
Henry Lee Swint (1909-1985) served on the faculty of the Vanderbilt University History Department from 1939 to 1985. Born and raised in southern Alabama, Swint received the Bachelor of Arts degree from Birmingham Southern College in 1929. In 1930, Vanderbilt awarded him the Master of Arts in history and he embarked on a college teaching career. Between 1930 and 1936, he taught at Louisburg College in Louisburg, North Carolina (1930-1931), King College in Bristol, Tennessee (1931-1934), and Middle Georgia State College in Cochran, Georgia (1934-1936). He began work toward the Ph.D. at Vanderbilt in 1936. After completing his dissertation on "The Northern Teacher in the South, 1862-1870" in 1939, he was appointed Instructor in Vanderbilt’s history department. He became an Assistant Professor in 1942 and progressed through the ranks until 1971, when he was appointed Holland N. McTyeire Professor of History. He held that chair until his death in 1985.
Vanderbilt University Press published Swint’s two books -- his dissertation (1941) and a second work entitled Dear Ones at Home: Letters from Contraband Camps (1966). Swint also wrote numerous book reviews and articles and served on the administrative board of the Andrew Jackson Papers. In 1969, the Executive Committee of the Board of Trust appointed Swint to research and write a history of Vanderbilt for the university’s centennial celebration in 1975. Swint worked on the project from 1969 to 1977, but did not complete it. Paul Conkin took up the project again in 1982 and incorporated Swint’s work into Gone With the Ivy: A Biography of Vanderbilt University (Knoxville: University of Tennessee Press, 1985).
Scope and Contents Note
The Henry Lee Swint Papers date from 1933 to 1978 and are comprised primarily of correspondence, writings, and research notes. Swint carried on an extensive correspondence with students, former students, and colleagues at other institutions, mainly discussing research interests and personal concerns. A more limited correspondence with faculty and other colleagues at Vanderbilt contains information regarding administrative matters, including controversial subjects such as the 1960 dismissal of Divinity School student James Lawson for participating in civil rights demonstrations in Nashville. The collection also includes a fairly extensive file of speeches and lecture notes, book reviews, article manuscripts and offprints, correspondence regarding Swint’s two books, and research notes on Vanderbilt’s history. The Swint Papers are organized into eight series, as follows:
Correspondence (4.35 cft.)
Writings (2 cft.)
Research Notes (3 cft.)
Student Work (2.7 cft.)
History Department (2.5 cft.)
University Committees and Other Administrative (.5 cft)
Institutes on Communism and American Democracy (.35 cft)
Tapes (3.35 cft.)
Elizabeth Swint Papers (.35 cft)
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Students
    - Alvord, Ellsworth C. (Box 1)
    - Aney, Al (Box 1)
    - Arnow, Harriett (Box 1)
    - Bacchus, James (Box 1)
    - Baker, William O. (Box 1)
    - Belanger, Yvonne (Box 1)
    - Belles, Gilbert (Box 1)
    - Braser, John (Box 1)
    - Brewer, Pat (Box 1)
    - Burke, W. J. (Box 1)
    - Burns, Chester R. (Box 1)
    - Bushnell, Paul E. (Box 1)
    - Calvert, Rae (Box 1)
    - Casey, Joe (Box 1)
    - Chambless, Martha (Box 1)
    - Chatfield, Charles (Box 1)
    - Clanton, Glen (Box 1)
    - Clarke, Robert S. (Box 1)
    - Climer, Pat (Box 1)
    - Conkin, Paul (Box 1)
    - Cooke, Jack (Box 1)
    - Cooper, Alan (Box 1)
    - Creekmore, Marion V. (Box 1)
    - Crocker, Helen (Box 1)
    - Crowe, J. Crawford (Box 1)
    - Curlee, Joan (Box 1)
    - Davis, Gerald (Box 1)
    - Davis, Hugh (Box 1)
    - Davidson, Donald (Box 1)
    - Diedrichs, Tripp T. (Box 1)
    - Dollar, Jesse (Box 1)
    - Donovan, Tocy (Box 1)
    - Droze, William (Box 1)
    - Drury, Pat (Box 1)
    - Edmondson, William D. (Box 1)
    - Edmonds, Tony (Box 1)
    - Fair, Harold L. (Box 1)
    - Feinstein, Estelle (Box 1)
    - Ferriss, William (Box 1)
    - Flynn, Ralph (Box 1)
    - Frazer, Nat (Box 1)
    - French, Mansfield J. (Box 1)
    - Fuller, R.C. (Box 1)
    - Gladwin, Lee A. (Box 1)
    - Gordon, Susie (Box 1)
    - Graves, John Temple, II (Box 1)
    - Grubbs, Don (Box 1)
    - Hackney, Sheldon (Box 1)
    - Hamilton, Charles (Box 1)
    - Harbison, Stan (Box 1)
    - Harrell, Edward (Box 1)
    - Harris, Tom (Box 1)
    - Hartje, Robert (Box 1)
    - Harvey, Charles (Box 1)
    - Heflin, Frank (Box 1)
    - Hinds, Harold (Box 1)
    - Hodes, Allen (Box 1)
    - Hodges, James (Box 1)
    - Howell, Sarah (Box 1)
    - Hubbard, Preston (Box 1)
    - Hyman, Ronald (Box 1)
    - Ingram, Pressley (Box 1)
    - Jacobson, Tim (Box 1)
    - Jarman, Claude (Box 1)
    - Johnson, Arthur (Box 1)
    - Johnstone, Bob (Box 1)
    - Kiger, Joseph C. (Box 1)
    - Landrith, Harold F. (Box 1)
    - Leverette, William (Box 1)
    - Lewis, William B. (Box 1)
    - Lisenby, Foy (Box 1)
    - Massey, Rich (Box 1)
    - May, Lynn (Box 1)
    - McCall, Dan (Box 1)
    - Miller, Glen (Box 1)
    - Minton, John (Box 1)
    - Morison, William J. (Box 1)
    - Neal, James (Box 1)
    - Nelsen, Anne K. (Box 1)
    - Nimmo, Joan (Box 1)
    - Nixon, Betty Chiles (Box 1)
    - Ordoubadian, Reza (Box 1)
    - Patterson, Robert Lynn (Box 1)
    - Phillips, Paul (Box 1)
    - Pitts, Bill (Box 1)
    - Polle, Charles H. (Box 1)
    - Porter, Curt (Box 1)
    - Rayfield, Jo Ann (Box 1)
    - Rezek, Philipp (Box 1)
    - Rutland, Robert (Box 1)
    - Sanders, Sylvia (Box 2)
    - Schulle-Nordholt, J.W. (Box 2)
    - Shelby, Lonnie (Box 2)
    - Sheppard, Tom (Box 2)
    - Shouse, Sarah N. (Box 2)
    - Simundson, Dan (Box 2)
    - Sloan, John (Box 2)
    - Smith, Lewis (Box 2)
    - Smith, Sam B. (Box 2)
    - South, O.D. (Box 2)
    - Spain, Rufus (Box 2)
    - Speier, Lamar (Box 2)
    - Spidle, Jake W., Jr. (Box 2)
    - Stevenson, Ed (Box 2)
    - Stevenson, George (Box 2)
    - Stocking, George W. (Box 2)
    - Student complaints (Box 2)
    - Sullinger, Ray H., Jr. (Box 2)
    - Swain, Martha (Box 2)
    - Talbert, Roy (Box 2)
    - Tanner, Doris (Box 2)
    - Tart, Steve (Box 2)
    - Tarver, Jack W., Jr. (Box 2)
    - Taylor, Elizabeth (Box 2)
    - Thompson, Bob (Box 2)
    - Tolbert, Betty Weaver (Box 2)
    - Turbeville, Gus (Box 2)
    - Tyler, Tom (Box 2)
    - Vaughan, Eugene (Box 2)
    - Venable, Austin (Box 2)
    - Venables, Robert (Box 2)
    - West, Ben (Box 2)
    - White, Charles (Box 2)
    - White, Edward (Box 2)
    - White, James (Box 2)
    - Willey, John (Box 2)
    - Williams, C.S. (Box 2)
    - Former Students, miscellaneous (3f) (Box 2)
    - Letters of recommendation (6f) (Box 2)
  - Professional
    - Abbott, Martin (Box 3)
    - Afro-American Studies (Box 3)
    - Alexander, Thomas (Box 3)
    - Allen, Clifford (Box 3)
    - Applewhite, Davis (Box 3)
    - Armbrister, Victor (Box 3)
    - Army correspondence, misc. (Box 3)
    - Bacon, Philip (Box 3)
    - Barnes, J. Ward (Box 3)
    - Bausch, Edward (Box 3)
    - Bell, E.S. (Box 3)
    - Bestor, A.E. (Box 3)
    - Beach, Leonard (Box 3)
    - Billington, Ray (Box 3)
    - Blake, Nelson (Box 3)
    - Brown, Ira (Box 3)
    - Bucke, E.S. (Box 3)
    - Burns, Edward M. (Box 3)
    - Campbell, E.Q. (Box 3)
    - Cappon, L.S. (Box 3)
    - Chappell, G. (Box 3)
    - Cheney, Frances N. (Box 3)
    - Clark, Thomas D. (Box 3)
    - Clinton, R. (Box 3)
    - Coles, Harry L. (Box 3)
    - Corlew, Robert R. (Box 3)
    - Crabb, A.L. (Box 3)
    - Cornish, Dudley (Box 3)
    - Crawford, Meredith (Box 3)
    - Crenshaw, Ollinger (Box 3)
    - Cresap, Bernie (Box 3)
    - Cross, Whitney R. (Box 3)
    - Current, Rich (Box 3)
    - Curry, W.C. (Box 3)
    - Curti, Merle (Box 3)
    - Davidson, Philip (Box 3)
    - Davis, Rich R. (Box 3)
    - Davis, Treadwell (Box 3)
    - Denbo, Bruce F. (Box 3)
    - Detweiler, Philip F. (Box 3)
    - Donnald M. (Box 3)
    - Durden, Robert (Box 3)
    - Davenport, Garvin (Box 3)
    - Donald, David (Box 3)
    - Durham, Walter T. (Box 3)
    - Elliott, Don (Box 3)
    - England, Merton (Box 3)
    - Ferguson, E.W. (Box 3)
    - Filler, Louis (Box 3)
    - Frie, Sidney (Box 3)
    - Fite, Gilbert (Box 3)
    - Fleming, Bond (Box 3)
    - Fletcher, Joe (Box 3)
    - Freidel, Frank (Box 3)
    - Franklin, John Hope (Box 3)
    - Futrell, Frank (Box 3)
    - Gabriel, R.H. (Box 3)
    - Garrison, Curtis W. (Box 3)
    - George, Scott (Box 3)
    - Gibbs, G.F. (Box 3)
    - Giddens, Lucien P. (Box 3)
    - Going, Allen J. (Box 3)
    - Graf, LeRoy (Box 3)
    - Grant, Pat (Box 3)
    - Green, Fletcher (Box 3)
    - Hardacre, Paul (Box 3)
    - Harrington, Fred Harvey (Box 3)
    - Hart, Laura L. (Box 3)
    - Hartz, Louis (Box 3)
    - Henderson, Gerald (Box 3)
    - Hicks, J.D. (Box 3)
    - Hill, Henry (Box 3)
    - Hoetink, Prof. (Box 3)
    - Hood, Howard (Box 3)
    - Hooper, Ernest (Box 3)
    - Howard, Milo (Box 3)
    - Huntley, M.D. (Box 3)
    - Jackson, Ed (Box 3)
    - Jeffries, Margaret Allison (Box 3)
    - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 3)
    - Jordan, Philip (Box 3)
    - Jordan, W.T. (Box 3)
    - Knight, Edgar W. (Box 3)
    - Kefauver, Estes (Box 3)
    - Kraus, Michael (Box 3)
    - Lagemann, Robert (Box 3)
    - Lanier, Charles (Box 3)
    - Lawson Case (Box 3)
    - Leach, Richard (Box 3)
    - Leopold, R. (Box 3)
    - Link, Arthur (Box 3)
    - Linn, Ralph (Box 3)
    - Lund, F. Edward (Box 3)
    - Massey, Mary E. (Box 3)
    - Mathews, Joe (Box 3)
    - McGaw, Robert A. (Box 3)
    - McPherson, James M. (Box 3)
    - Minnich, Dot (Box 3)
    - Mooney, C.C. (Box 3)
    - Moore, A.B. (Box 3)
    - Moore, G. (Box 3)
    - Moore, R.E. (Box 3)
    - Morton, R.L. (Box 3)
    - McLemure, R.A. (Box 3)
    - Meroney, V. (Box 3)
    - Moffett, Charles H. [Lawson case] (Box 3)
    - Nagel, P. (Box 3)
    - Norton, E.B. (Box 3)
    - Norton, H. (Box 3)
    - Owsley, Frank (Box 3)
    - Patrick, R.W. (Box 3)
    - Peabody (Box 3)
    - Peterson, William (Box 3)
    - Pettit, Jean (Box 3)
    - Pomfret, John (Box 3)
    - Posey, Walter (Box 3)
    - Protocols of Zion (Box 3)
    - ROTC (Box 3)
    - Purdy, R.R. (Box 3)
    - Reed Case (Box 3)
    - Robb, F. (Box 3)
    - Robbins, Cecil W. (Box 3)
    - Rundell, Walter, Jr. (Box 3)
    - Rose, Willie Lee (Box 3)
    - Russell, Richard B. (Box 3)
    - Searcy, Robert (Box 3)
    - Sensabaugh, Leon (Box 3)
    - Shafer, Boyd C. (Box 3)
    - Shanks, Henry T. (Box 3)
    - Silver, James W. (Box 3)
    - Smith, T.L. (Box 3)
    - Southand, S. (Box 3)
    - Steely, Frank (Box 3)
    - Stephenson, W.N. (Box 3)
    - Stokely, Wilma Dykeman (Box 3)
    - Strout, C. (Box 3)
    - Sturdivant, Robert W. (Box 3)
    - Sullivan, Mark (Box 3)
    - Summersell, Charles G. (Box 3)
    - Sutherland, Jane (Box 3)
    - Tate, Vernon (Box 3)
    - Taylor, Harold (Box 3)
    - Tennessee Historical Quarterly (Box 3)
    - Tennessee State Library and Archives (Box 3)
    - Thomas, C.M. (Box 3)
    - Thompson, Bob P. (Box 3)
    - Trexler, H.A. (Box 3)
    - Tinsley, James (Box 3)
    - Tryon, W.S. (Box 3)
    - Vanderbilt, Harold (Box 4)
    - Vanderbilt University Press (Box 4)
    - Vandiver, Frank (Box 4)
    - Walker, C.H. (Box 4)
    - Walker, Peter (Box 4)
    - Wall, Bennett H. (Box 4)
    - Walters, Bennett (Box 4)
    - Warren, Harris (Box 4)
    - Weisenberger, Francis P. (Box 4)
    - West End Methodist Episcopal Church (Box 4)
    - Wiley, Bell (Box 4)
    - Williams, Clanton (Box 4)
    - Williams, F. (Box 4)
    - Williams, Frank (Box 4)
    - Williams, T.H. (Box 4)
    - Williamson, Joel (Box 4)
    - Winther, Oscar O. (Box 4)
    - Wirth, Fremont P. (Box 4)
    - Woodrow Wilson Fellowship Program (Box 4)
    - Woods, Frank A. (Box 4)
    - Woodward, C. Vann (Box 4)
    - Wyllie, Irvin G. (Box 4)
    - Young, Harvey (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (3f) (Box 4)
  - Faculty
    - [Department] (Box 4)
    - Aden, John (Box 4)
    - Beach, Leonard B. (Box 4)
    - Binkley, William Campbell (Box 4)
    - Bingham, John (Box 4)
    - Boorman, Howard L. (Box 4)
    - Boutwell, Sidney F. (Box 4)
    - Bradley, Harold W. (Box 4)
    - Branscomb, Harvie (Box 4)
    - Caldwell, John (Box 4)
    - Carmichael, O.C. (Box 4)
    - Carmichael, O.C., Jr. (Box 4)
    - Carr, Jeff (Box 4)
    - Christie, Amos (Box 4)
    - Davidson, Philip (Box 4)
    - Delzell, Charles F. (Box 4)
    - Ericksen, Stan (Box 4)
    - Fields, Emmet B. (Box 4)
    - Grantham, Dewey (Box 4)
    - Fleming, D.F. (Box 4)
    - Fleming, W.L. (Box 4)
    - Gulley, Frank, Jr. (Box 4)
    - Georgescu, Nicholas (Box 4)
    - Hanser, A.S. (Box 4)
    - Hardacre, Paul H. (Box 4)
    - Harris, Robert (Box 4)
    - Hobbs, Nicholas (Box 4)
    - Holladay, W.G. (Box 4)
    - Kaser, David (Box 4)
    - Lagemann, R.T. (Box 4)
    - Land, A.C. (Box 4)
    - Leach, Doug (Box 4)
    - Lehmann, Joseph (Box 4)
    - Lindgren, Roy (Box 4)
    - Lively, Robert (Box 4)
    - Marchant, A. (Box 4)
    - Mayhew, George (Box 4)
    - Owsley, Frank L. (Box 4)
    - Purdy, R.R. (Box 4)
    - Robison, Dan M. (Box 4)
    - Shahan, Ewing P. (Box 4)
    - Smith, George (Box 4)
    - Stahlman, Mildred (Box 4)
    - Sussman, George (Box 4)
    - Van Sickle, J.V. (Box 4)
    - Voegeli, Jacque (Box 4)
    - Weaver, Herbert (Box 4)
    - Winters, Don (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Personal
    - John Hancock Life Insurance Company (Box 4)
    - McMurray Realty (Box 4)
  - Manuscripts Collecting
    - General (Box 4)
    - American Legion Project (Box 4)
    - Leads (Box 4)
  - Genealogy
    - Badger, Loretta M. (Box 5)
    - Bailey, Yvonne (Box 5)
    - Bradley, Shirley S. (Box 5)
    - Breed, Kermit L. (Box 5)
    - Ewing, Burt (Box 5)
    - Fernandez, Betty (Box 5)
    - Greer, Fred W. (Box 5)
    - Gunby, Norma (Box 5)
    - Jones, Jeannette (Box 5)
    - McGraw, Jan (Box 5)
    - Mullins, Alice S. (Box 5)
    - Pratt, Mirtie (Box 5)
    - Reeves, Lee (Box 5)
    - Sovine, Phyllis (Box 5)
    - Stiefel, Frances Ann (Box 5)
    - Swint, Arthur W. (Box 5)
    - Swint, B.F. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Charles (Box 5)
    - Swint, David C. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Earl (Box 5)
    - Swint, Edwin (Box 5)
    - Swint, Elizabeth (Box 5)
    - Swint, Elvin (Box 5)
    - Swint, Emmett (Box 5)
    - Swint, Grace (Box 5)
    - Swint, Jimmy (Box 5)
    - Swint, John (Ark.) (Box 5)
    - Swint, John (Calf.) (Box 5)
    - Swint, John E. (Box 5)
    - Swint, John S. (Box 5)
    - Swint, John W. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Jude (Box 5)
    - Swint, Kathy (Box 5)
    - Swint, Kaye (Box 5)
    - Swint, Lois (Texas) (Box 5)
    - Swint, Lois (Utah) (Box 5)
    - Swint, Marie W. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Marshall (Box 5)
    - Swint, Mose (Box 5)
    - Swint, Ollie D. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Oswell (Box 5)
    - Swint, Richard B. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Robert (Box 5)
    - Swint, Robert L. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Ronald (Box 5)
    - Swint, Rosa (Box 5)
    - Swint, Rose (Box 5)
    - Swint, Ruth (Box 5)
    - Swint, Sarah (Box 5)
    - Swint, Thomas R. (Box 5)
    - Swint, W.C. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Wallace (Box 5)
    - Swint, Walter (Box 5)
    - Swint, William B. (Box 5)
    - Swint, Wyatt A. (Box 5)
    - Thompson, Faye (Box 5)
    - Wilkins, Pearl (Box 5)
- Series II: Writings
  - Speeches, Lectures
    - Correspondence regarding, 1942-75 (incl.) (Box 6)
    - Programs, schedules, etc. (Box 6)
    - Alumni -- Memphis, 3/19/72 (Box 6)
    - Alumni -- Tupelo, MS, 4/74 (Box 6)
    - [American Democracy] -- Educational Television Series, 8/13/64 (Box 6)
    - American Interest in the Near East -- Florence, AL, 1946 (Box 6)
    - Arkansas State College Lecture Series, June 1966 (Box 6)
    - [Conflict in American History] -- [Houston], nd (Box 6)
    - [Democracy] -- Lenten Forum, West End Methodist Episcopal Church (Box 6)
    - Education and Democracy (Box 6)
    - [Education of Blacks], nd (Box 6)
    - Europe to America: The Transit of Old World Thought to New, 6/22/55 (Box 6)
    - European Influence on Southern Educators, 1876-1900 -- Knoxville, TN, 1958 (Box 6)
    - Edwin Booth -- King College, Bristol, TN, 11/16/33 (Box 6)
    - [Francis Asbury], nd (Box 6)
    - Franklin, TN, nd (Box 6)
    - Freshman orientation, Vanderbilt University (Box 6)
    - Historical Activities of the State of Tennessee, nd (Box 6)
    - [History] -- West End Methodist Episcopal Church, [1960] (Box 6)
    - [Individual Freedom], c., 1976 (Box 6)
    - Italo-Ethiopian Crisis -- Cochran, GA, 11/24/35 (Box 6)
    - King College, Bristol, TN, c., 1931-1934 (Box 6)
    - [Middle East] -- Ft. Campbell, KY, 1946 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous unidentified lecture notes (2f) (Box 6)
    - [Nashville] -- Torch Club, Nashville, May, 1971 (Box 6)
    - [Northern Teachers in the South] -- Eldorado, Ill., 1947 (Box 6)
    - The Old Order Changeth -- Commencement address, Florence StateTeachers College, 5/25/48 (Box 6)
    - On the Teaching of History -- District Educational Conference, Abingdon, VA, 1933 (Box 6)
    - Problem of Validity in Historical Study, nd (Box 6)
    - Race -- Boone, 4/15/70 (Box 6)
    - Race and Racism -- Johnson City, TN, 4/11/70 (Box 6)
    - [Race and Racism] -- Torch Club (Box 6)
    - Radio, 1942-43 (Box 6)
    - Sam Davis Memorial, 10/8/79 (Box 6)
    - Television -- Bristol, TN, nd (Box 6)
    - Tension and Persistence in Higher Education -- Phi Beta Kappa, 5/7/73 (Box 6)
    - Vanderbilt University History (Box 6)
    - War and Peace -- ROTC Commissioning Ceremony, May 1974 (Box 6)
    - “Westward, Look, the Land is Bright" -- Commencement address, Deshler High School, Sheffield, AL, 6/2/47 (Box 6)
    - [Women], PEO, 10/5/78 (Box 6)
  - Books and Articles
    - Dear Ones at Home: Letters from Contraband Camps -- correspondence and reviews, c. 1967-68 (4f) (Box 7)
    - The Northern Teacher in the South, 1862-1870 -- correspondence, 1946-59, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Book reviews by Swint (Box 7)
      Note card listing
      Offprints
      Typescripts (2f)
    - Correspondence regarding articles, 1959-66 (Box 7)
    - “Birdseye,” fragment, nd (Box 7)
    - “Determinism in America, 1875-1900,”, nd (Box 7)
    - “Effects of Supreme Court Decision,”, 1/23/36 (Box 7)
    - “Everything Not Nailed Down is Coming Loose,” Vanderbilt University Alumnus, Jan.-Feb., 1969 (Box 7)
    - “Great American Century,” Arkansas Historical Quarterly xxiv (4), Winter 1965, 355-368 (Box 7)
    - “Higher Education in the Tennessee and Kentucky Region a Century Ago,”, 1964 (Box 7)
    - “A Historian’s Letter to University Librarians,”, nd (Box 7)
    - “History: Mirror or Crystal Ball?,” Vanderbilt University Alumnus, 3/19/72 (Box 7)
    - “Ho! For Arkansas,” Arkansas Historical Quarterly xxiv (3), Autumn 1965, 195-207 (Box 7)
    - “Mason-Dixon,” Encyclopedia Brittanica, 1959 (Box 7)
    - “Reforming Generation,”, nd (Box 7)
    - “Sectionalism and Nationalism,”, 2/15/69 (Box 7)
    - “Some Recent Political Trends,”, 1933 (Box 7)
    - “Trends in the Teaching of Social and Intellectual History,” 11/55 (Box 7)
    - “The Utopian Dream of American Reformers,” Peabody Reflector xxx (1), January 1957 (Box 7)
- Series III: Research Notes
  - Baptists
  - Greenbelt, Maryland
  - Historiography
  - Mims, Edwin -- “Six Decades of Southern Education”
  - Pelley Publications (anti-Semitism)
  - Religion
  - South
  - Tennessee State Library and Archives Registers
    - Manuscripts on Microfilm (typescript list), nd (Box 8)
    - Preliminary Checklist of Tennessee Legislative Documents, 1954 (Box 8)
    - Checklist of Microfilm in the Tennessee State Archives, 1960 (Box 8)
    - Checklist of Microfilm in the Tennessee State Archives, Revised, 1963 (Box 8)
    - Checklist of Microfilm in the Manuscripts Division, Tennessee State Library and Archives: A Supplement, 1965 (Box 8)
    - Numbered Registers: (Box 8)
      1. Jacob McGavock Dickinson Papers (two copies 1959, two copies revised 1964)
      3. Walter Wagner Faw Papers, 1961
      5. J. Emerick Nagy Collection, Nashville Public Schools, 1962
      6. Zilphia Horton Folk Music Collection, 1964
      7. Buell-Brian Papers, 1964
      9. Highlander Folk School Audio Collection, 1964
      10. Civil War Collection, Confederate and Federal, 1966
      11. Cherokee Collection, 1966
      12. Jones Family Papers, 1966
    - Directory of Churches, Missions, and Religious Institutions of Tennessee, No. 19: Davidson County, (WPA,1940) (Box 8)
  - Vanderbilt University Historical Sketches -- Biographical
    - Branscomb, Harvie (Box 8)
    - Carmichael, Oliver C. (Box 8)
    - Heard, George Alexander (Box 8)
    - Sarratt, Charles Madison (Box 8)
  - Vanderbilt University Historical Sketches -- Subjects
    - Academic (Box 8)
    - Administration, 1873-1973 -- Chancellor, Senate, Standing Committees (Box 8)
    - Administration -- Trends (Box 8)
    - Administrative Board -- Presidents (Box 8)
    - Agrarians (Box 8)
    - Athletics (Box 8)
    - Board of Trust (Box 8)
    - College of Arts and Sciences -- Curriculum (Box 8)
    - College of Arts and Sciences -- Faculty, 1875-1973 (4f) (Box 8)
    - Finance (Box 8)
    - Founding (Box 8)
    - Military (Box 8)
    - Physical Plant (Box 8)
    - Regionalism, Nationalism, Internationalism (Box 8)
    - Students (Box 8)
    - Students -- Self-Government (Box 8)
    - University Center (Box 8)
  - Note cards (Box 9)
  - Note cards (Box 10)
- Series IV: Student Work
  - Note cards (Box 11)
  - Reports on readings, History 285/385
  - Masters thesis proposals:
    - Cross, Wallas (Box 12)
    - Dickinson, Ann (Box 12)
    - Friedman, Randi (Box 12)
    - Hunn, Jim (Box 12)
    - Jarnagin, Laura (Box 12)
    - Lahutsky, Nadia (Box 12)
    - Nelson, Anne (Box 12)
    - Pace, Robert S. (Box 12)
    - Willis, M.A. (Box 12)
  - Honors Thesis (2 copies) -- Gilliam, Harriet, “Beauty in Their Tragedy: A Comparison of Ethical Concepts in the Writings of Ernest Hemingway and Reinhold Niebuhr”, (1966)
  - Student Seminar Papers (arranged topically; number of papers on topic provided in parentheses if more than one)
    - 1920s (Box 12)
    - Adams, Henry (Box 12)
    - American Economic Association (Box 12)
    - Art (Box 12)
    - Bank of the United States (Box 12)
    - Barton, William E. (Box 12)
    - Becker, Carl (Box 12)
    - Beecher Family (Box 12)
    - Bilbo Era (Box 12)
    - Bryan, William Jennings (Box 12)
    - Caribbean Policy, U.S. (Box 12)
    - City (Box 12)
    - Colonial Mobs (Box 12)
    - Colyar, A.S. (Box 12)
    - Conservatism (2) (Box 12)
    - Darrow, Clarence (Box 12)
    - Debs, Eugene V. (Box 12)
    - Determinism (2) (Box 12)
    - Dewey, John (2) (Box 12)
    - Dickinson, Jacob McGavock (Box 12)
    - Dubois, W.E.B. (2) (Box 12)
    - Eaton, John, Jr., General (Box 12)
    - Education (3) (Box 12)
    - Evolution (Box 12)
    - Fall, Philip Slater (Box 12)
    - Ford, Henry (Box 12)